<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Highnesse the Lord Protector-protected in his accepting, or (if you will have it so) in his assuming the protectorship as is here cautioned, and all the clamors, cavils, exceptions, and objections against either as unlawful or king-like (as some please to call it) fully refuted and answered, or satisfied &amp;c. : written in honour of His Highness, so of all our other present powers whether creators or createds, to quit them of the aspersions of usurpers or unlawful powers ... likewise the peoples rights and liberties are fully maintain'd ... lastly all exceptions against the ordinance about treason answered, and it's conceived that it were treason not to make such an ordinance / [by] S.H., senior.</title>
            <author>Hunton, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11299845</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11299845</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1464:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Highnesse the Lord Protector-protected in his accepting, or (if you will have it so) in his assuming the protectorship as is here cautioned, and all the clamors, cavils, exceptions, and objections against either as unlawful or king-like (as some please to call it) fully refuted and answered, or satisfied &amp;c. : written in honour of His Highness, so of all our other present powers whether creators or createds, to quit them of the aspersions of usurpers or unlawful powers ... likewise the peoples rights and liberties are fully maintain'd ... lastly all exceptions against the ordinance about treason answered, and it's conceived that it were treason not to make such an ordinance / [by] S.H., senior.</title>
                  <author>Hunton, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Ley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Samuel Hunton.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47355:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47355:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HIS HIGHNESSE THE Lord Protector-protected:</p>
            <p>In his accepting, or (if you will have it ſo) in his aſſuming the Protectorſhip, as is here cautioned, and all the clamors, cavils, exceptions, and objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt either, as unlawful, or King-like (as ſome pleaſe to call it) fully refuted, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, or ſatisfied, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>VVritten in Honor of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> ſo of all our other preſent Powers, whether Creators, or Createds, to quit them of the aſperſions of Uſurpers, or unlawful Powers, and to quell or qualifie their Oppoſers, and render the ſaid Powers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, as they are in point of Power; as for execution of their ſaid Powers, it concerns them to ſee to themſelves, as it doth us all to allow them their grains of weight, which the weightieſt muſt be allow'd, even the Exceptors own ſelf.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the Peoples Rights and Liberties are fully maintain'd, as either ſide are capable of maintaining them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, all exceptions againſt the Ordinance about TREASON anſwered, and it's conceived, that it were Treaſon not to make ſuch an ORDINANCE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And the eyes of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> were on the son of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> or <hi>David,</hi> as wiſer and abler in his in and out-goings, then any of all <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants, ſo that <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf was afraid of him, for that he ſaw the Lord was with him,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Samuel 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Read all, or nothing at all; alſo judg judiciouſly, and ingenuouſly, or not at all; for it's againſt the Law of Romans, Heathens, and Pagans, to judg of any one, or any thing, before throughly underſtood.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>S. H.</hi> Senior.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Ley</hi> at <hi>Pauls-Chain,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47355:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47355:2"/>
            <head>To his Highneſſe the LORD PROTECTOR.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NEw occaſions do neceſſarily invite to this ſecond Dedication, as relating to the firſt, to wait on you alſo; your ſervant doth humbly intreat your Highneſs pardon of this his neceſsitated preſumption, by reaſon of the aforeſaid reaſon; alſo your acceptance and faireſt conſtruction of his upright intentions, and he will not be further offenſive by prolix inlargement, ſeeing the inſuings will in their due places, ſay what more is to be ſaid, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he makes bold to ſubſcribe himſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſs most humble<lb/> ſervant,<lb/> 
                  <hi>Samuel Hunton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:47355:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am in a manner by our ſuddain alterations call'd to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome things, and add alſo, to ſecond my firſt man, leaſt he be over-man'd by new clamors, &amp;c. for ſure I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not now ſcape branding for a Time-ſerver, a flatterer, and what not? be it as it will, though I will otherwiſe, for ſuch thou ſhalt not find me, though I ſhould find thee ſuch. In ſhort, no <hi>Sanballats</hi> neither ought, nor ſhall deviate me from my duties of any nature; more I have not to ſay, for that the followings will ſay it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So I reſt thy ſervant, as thou art judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ingenuous (elſe do what thou canſt, thou art mine.)<lb/> 
                  <hi>S. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>REad the Margent I pray thee alſo, that ſo thou mayeſt not come ſhort of my intentions; and if then thou beeſt not fully ſatisfied, ſee our <hi>Army-Armed</hi> ſold by Mr. <hi>William Ley</hi> at <hi>Pauls-Chain.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47355:3"/>
            <head>The Lord Protector protected, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur former Tract of the Army-Armed, were it well minded, might have ſpared this ſecond; but moſt Readers are incomprehenſive, and the comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive inconſiderate; it's a hard task then, to make things (though good) good to uncapable, wilfull, or bad men, for we hear already, and that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by an <hi>Idea'd Proſopopoeia</hi> of all ſorts of wills, minds, humours, partyes, and factions, what they are apt to ſay, but perſonally alſo what divers in part have and do ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> theſe or the like ſayings, clamors, and exclamations following; So, Now we are abſolute Slaves, farewel then our Laws, and Liberties, and <hi>ad placitum,</hi> our lives alſo, for the Souldiery will and may as they liſt, and we as we can; we ſee plainly that the Sword domineers, rules, and revels it, and plays reaks circularly, for it ſelfly diſſolves, and then creates, and then diſſolves again our <hi>Parliaments, ad placitum,</hi> and ſo recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates it ſelf with ſuch paſtimes, it turn'd from, and would none of Monarchy, nor Kinghood, but<note n="*" place="margin">As our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by reaſon of confuſed aims, ends, judgements, and opinions.</note> Anarchy only, that ſo it might turn to them the better, to ſerve its own turn, for it did but out-face them, and then face about, and ſo turn'd to both again, and Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy alſo; ſo we are where, and as we were, only<note n="†" place="margin">Diviſions b. Sects, as call'd, which now are remedied with justice and ſafety, by the 37. Article, for an in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced conſent with a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people, would can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>found all</note> Anarchy is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſubſtract, divide, and confound us. Names, Perſons, and ſome Preſentments are changed, but natures are the ſame; why then all this ado, except to undo all? If Kinghood was intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as it was pretended againſt, why kept we not him we had? or why have we not him we ſhould have? and laſt of all, why have we him we ſhould not have? why, ſay others, any <hi>King</hi> at all?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47355:4"/>why not rather <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>Councels</hi> of <hi>State?</hi> are not <hi>Hogen-Mogens,</hi> high and mighty States and Powers, ſtately Governments and titles? why alſo the Army diſſolve the firſt Parliament? and then create and unſtate the ſecond, without the ſaid Parliaments or peoples conſent, and then ſelfly reſolve and diſſolve all things, <hi>ad placitum?</hi> why the Protectorſhip aſſum'd? or if confer'd, why by a party only? why not the whole Parliament inveſt the inveſted? or is't not rather a formal inveſture, as fearing force? or chooſe they not cunningly to be choſen? alſo to countenance the choſen, as if of Free-choice, and ſo Authentick to colour and hide Uſurpation? For ſure the <hi>Sword,</hi> like the <hi>Sworded Angel,</hi> which with his Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chunt anh threatning <hi>Blade,</hi> awed <hi>Adam</hi> from returning to his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Kinghood</hi> again, and reſerved it for his own<note n="*" place="margin">Cjed.</note> 
               <hi>King;</hi> ſo our <hi>Sword</hi> awes all <hi>Adams</hi> and <hi>Eves</hi> too, from returning to invade this reſerved Kingdom, this <hi>Edon,</hi> this Paradiſe, and place of bliſs and pleaſure, and hath made this Angel its Guardian, whoſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſht blade muſt keep them at an awful diſtance, from acceſſing, till he<note n="†" place="margin">By death.</note> receſs, leaſt they approach to their reproach, the Golden Scepter without its<note n="*" place="margin">Till choſen.</note> extention, or holding out, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I have purpoſely rendered it as high as it can well be, that ſo anſwering all thoſe exceptions, which ſeem almoſt unanſwerable, we ſhall ſilence all inſolent Excepters: For had I not for'd ſo high, I ſhould have been overtopt, and outbrav'd as not anſwered, nor anſwerable, much to the diſhonor of our preſent and future Powers, yet whats already done, hath done it, but cauſe not rendred in their taunting Dialect, though yet <hi>dialectically,</hi> they either cannot, or will not ſee it, nor it may be can many of our Readers read our meaning in our other anſwer, to anſwer theſe, ſo it falls to our ſhare to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, to give circular ſatisfaction, which we will do the beſt we can, What wilt thou ſay then, if I prove, that thou, ſo each Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual in the whole Nation that excepts, have done their ſhares, in what they except againſt: Sure I ſhall go neer, (if rational thou beeſt) to compreſs thee for future, but if irrational, thou deſerveſt ſuppreſſion, for why ſhould Beaſts rank, or Rival it with men?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Know then weaklings, that the firſt Parliament was choſen by each individual in the whole Nation, and ſo by thee that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteſt, yea by thoſe uncapable of chooſing, as by Wives, Children, and Servants, who yet choſe incluſively by their Husbands, Parents
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47355:4"/>and pay-Maſters; and as for any others that parſonally chooſe not, they yet chooſe alſo incluſively in the chooſers capable of chooſing, by Lawes, Conſent, or Cuſtome, that ſuch ſo landed, qualified and degreed ſhall chooſe; thus the childe in the Mothers lap chooſeth alſo, though it vocally choſe not,</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the Parliament ſo choſen, all refer themſelves, by way of betruſt, for all things apparently conduceing, and for doubtfuls to the hopefuleſt and moſt promiſings; and if then errors be, to bear them as they muſt their own in the like caſe,<note place="margin">† Note, all done by any Parliament, is the Act of the People, each Individual, but plain ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common good. So thou wilt find all thou objecteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, done by thy ſelf, except ſuch.</note> but whats apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the common good; thats not the peoples act, for it's beſides, or againſt the end of betruſt, ſo the people are not bound to it in right, yet might will bind them, and each individual is in right bound alſo, rather then wrong one another, or indanger the general.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Well, thus by thee, ſo each individual, a Parliament is created, and refer'd to as before; and this Parliament ſo created, creates an Army for univerſal defence, as of themſelves and thee, ſo of the three Nations, and Heads his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> head thereof, impowring him to ſupply with, or ſupplant, impower or diſpower Souldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all ſorts as conduceth; thus this <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Souldiery</hi> alſo are choſen, and impowered by thoe, as by thy chooſers, thy Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for defenders of the three Nations as afore; and the chiefe Commanders place intitles him Lord, and thy Parliament, and ſo thy ſelf hath ſo intitled him alſo; and Defender is in nature Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, for ſure Defenders are Protectors, and Protectors are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders and in nature no more: Theſe titles then were his by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his power and place before he thus had them, and are only now articulated, and not conferred, ſure then an aſſumption of them, had not been preſumption: The King was called the <hi>Faiths Defender,</hi> might he not then call himſelf its <hi>Protector?</hi> ſure he might, what's the diſcrimen? what's the crimen to call ſo?</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Highneſs</hi> alſo was his due before, if to be higheſt in point of juſt power and truſt will allow thereof, which <hi>Protectors</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders</hi> muſt be; ſure higheſt the ſuperlative, will allow of highneſs a poſitive or near it: ſuppoſe the firſt Parliament higheſt in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putative right, yet higheſt in juſt might will and juſtly may diſpute it, yea with Kings as call'd, to make ſure work for his own, his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery, and his Countries right, welfares and ſafeties, over which as a <hi>Protector</hi> he was put and betruſted, and anſwerably may impower,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47355:5"/>diſpower and over-power any power whatſoever, elſe he cannot circularly defend and protect; if he cannot, as occaſion is, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate alſo the very protected, if they offenſively oppoſe the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> or any protecteds: If this Power then be not capable of all I have ſaid, I know not what is, ſo not what to ſay, nor what I have ſaid: I ſay not, that he may in right <hi>ad libitum,</hi> do as he liſt, (though by Might he may, yet I hope will not) for he is bound by his oath and betruſt, to all univerſal conducings, and to individuals, not claſhing there with, nor with individual Juſtice, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Beſides the aforeſaid choice of him, as the higheſt and chiefeſt Power by the whole Nation, and ſo each individual, and ſo thy ſelf by thy firſt Parliament, I have proved in the Army-Armed, at page 9. Sect. 1. to the end, that the whole Nation, and ſo thy ſelf, and each individual, choſe, impowred, and intitled him, as afore, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time alſo.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſay, and prove, that his own, ſo the whole Nations ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of peace,<note place="margin">Theſe three wayes of choice quit from uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> welfare, and ſafety, might chooſe him the third time, and impower and intitle him, as afore. I ſay then, that this laſt choice alone may juſtifie all, if the<note n="*" place="margin">The common good and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> end of all be made good in the end. Sure then this threefold cord will fortifie, if uſed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly:</p>
            <p n="8">8. But thou ſayeſt, that this Power is in nature, (though not in name) Kinghood and Monarchy; be it ſo to pleaſe thee, why yet excepteſt thou at what by all our arguments and his threefold cord is, as afore, thy own act, and what (it may be) neceſſitated condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings make his alſo, for the better, quicker, and ſafer conduct of all things, then by Parliaments alone, of which thou canſt not judg, yet wilt; and they better can, ſo may, and will.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Thou ſayeſt alſo, that he hath Honors, Titles, and Revenues; likewiſe, a Retinue or Train of Attendance and State, and an eſtate King-like; this I know not, ſo will not diſpute; but be it ſo, it matters not, for I have already ſatisfied thee that it's thine owne act, or however thou ſhalt be ſatisfied before I have done with thee.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Thou goeſt on, why except againſt Kinghood, yet now <hi>King it? ſo it was only to unking, to King it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly no wiſdome can foreſee what experience and time may ſhew in their ſeaſon; if our wiſers now by experience and a further inſight, find that this our now Kinghood, as thou call'ſt it, and as it now is, or may be qualified, is as, or more hopeful and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47355:5"/>promiſing, though yet hazardable, as are all Governments; alſo more ſuiting to the glory and the bravery of our Nation,<note place="margin">Vain. glory, as call'd, may not be in vain.</note> and the conſtitution of the people, whom in general no other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeems ſo well to content; alſo conſidering Parliaments alone hitherto have not anſwered their expectations almoſt in any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, by reaſon of factions and diviſions, ſo of delayes, or not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at all, beſides many other objections and exceptions as are made againſt them, of which I judg not, nor can, but leave it to my Judges, who ſeem to judg ſo: I ſay then, ſeeing we muſt venture on ſome Government, and that now our Governours, as afore, find by experience this of the Protectorſhip as qualified, is as hopefull and promiſing as any, and in ſome things (as they conceive) before them; by their preferring it afore them: Can the wiſe blame the wiſe, if ſeeing their errors of ruining, for righting; they now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better inform'd, reform; the wiſeſt have their weakneſſes, and the beſt ſome wickedneſs; the wiſe muſt needs fail, where wiſdom is only had by experience, ſo they were ignorant before, yet not fools, though not ſo wiſe; for nothing is blind (though it ſee not) till capable of ſight, but when we ſee, ſhall we not give each co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour its due, 'cauſe when blind, we judg'd them all black?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Thou ſeeſt then that there might be good reaſons why Kinghood was declin'd, and yet now (as qualifi'd) inclin'd to, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick then, nor the Lawes of Love allow thee to conclude abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or certainly from uncertainties; nor to cenſure where thou oughteſt to reſpite or remiſs it, till certain; How then is't, thou ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abſolutely ſayeſt, They did unking, to King it, as thou pleaſeſt to call the Protectorſhip, ſeeing they might unking to State it, though now again with ſome cautions and conſiderations they unſtate to King it, as thou call'ſt it? Thou yet goeſt on, Why then not keep our firſt King, &amp;c. but ruine him, for righting him, or why not inright our ſecond, his firſt Son, &amp;c?</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Certainly didſt thou mind what thou readeſt, thou would not thus query things out of queſtion. I tell thee once more, we could not foreſee what we now ſee of Parliaments, by reaſon of their own, their friends, and chooſers ends and aims; nor could we foreſee, nor had we power (had we ſeen) to ſet right that King who had wrong'd all, and ſo over-king'd it, for Majeſty will not be eaſily over-maſtered, only will cunningly comply, to gather ſtrength to re-maſter it, nor was it fit in Juſtice to let one ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47355:6"/>go free, for ſo all future Powers might preſume, who now are forewarn'd what to truſt to; and for his Son, he is juſtly puniſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as well as his Father, for ſiding with his Father againſt both: Their Fathers the people,<note place="margin">As the people are their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c.</note> in treacheries, murthers, and paracides, rapes, and rapines, &amp;c. and the whole ſtock is juſtly ſtocke up, leaſt any of its ſhoots or branches (bramble-like) taking root, ſhould root us out, and bring in the Scot to top us, and then over-top us.</p>
            <p n="13">13. But once more to anſwer and ſilence thee fully by thy ſelf in theſe particulars alſo, as in the reſt; its thou, I ſay, each individual that excepteſt, haſt by thy Parliaments and Powers, as afore, done what thou excepteſt againſt, its thou then by them haſt executed the firſt King and outed the ſecond King, his Son, and with him the whole Seed; its thou that created, and then uncreated thy firſt Parliament, by Petitioning againſt them, and then created a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Parliament, by thy Powers left in the firſt Parliaments places, and then diſſolved them again by the ſaid Powers, and now laſt of all advanced, and heightned the ſaid Powers, in Power, Titles, State, and Eſtate, or Revenue, and Retinue, &amp;c. againſt all which thou ſo objecteſt, and excepteſt. See the <hi>Army-Armed</hi> page 4. Sect. 7. ſo page 9. to the end.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Well, we have not yet done, for it's objected, that his Choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers choſe him, to be choſen of or by him, and of fear, leaſt infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. I anſwer, this is ſurmize, not knowledg; ſo is't, as afore, againſt the Laws of Love and Logick, ſo alſo of Romans, Heathens, and Pagans, to judg the<note n="†" place="margin">Till try'd.</note> unjudgable, &amp;c. I anſwer, yet further, admit both crue, yet both are falſe, in reſpect of thy inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for they advantage not the Objecter, but are againſt him, and for the objected againſt; for if they chooſe him, they could not but chooſe, it was wiſely done to make a vertue of neceſſity, and with a wiſe and wary fear to provent force, which not thou proveſt not, and if thou doſt, its of no force, as thou ſholt find, ſeeing alſo experience of his wiſdom, faithfulneſs, and fortitude, choſe him to their hands, how then can they do otherwiſe then chooſe the ſo choſen, ſeeing ſome Governours, or Governour, and Government muſt be choſen and ventured on? All arguments then, both from God and man, bid them chooſe and venture on the Son of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then on any of the Sons of <hi>Kiſh,</hi> as not on any of <hi>Sauls</hi> Sons, or on any of all his Princes; people, or ſervants, 'cauſe the Son of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> was wiſer in his in and out-goings with <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants, then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47355:6"/>them all, ſo that the eyes of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> obſerved it, and that ſo, as <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf was afraid thereof, and his beloved <hi>Ionathan</hi> know, and acknowledged as much to <hi>David</hi> his lover, and beloved.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Ob.</hi> They choſe him to colour and hide Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for Uſurpation, I have anſwered it in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that it is not, and were it, yet with our cautions, it anſwers for it ſelf: But I ſay further, it's wiſdome to give as good a countenance as may be, even to things lawful, which ſelfly needs them not, yet needs them to relieve againſt diſcountenancing, by depraveds, and diſcontenteds.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Ob.</hi> Yet again, our Liberties are loſt, and we are abſolute Slaves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For loſt Liberties, ſee the looſers who, and why, and how they will, for any thing I can ſee, yet looſe them,<note place="margin">See page <hi>3.</hi> to the end of the Army-Armed</note> ſo may they know whom to blame; but if more be taken then are loſt, or the loſt not reſtored, as the looſers find themſelves, or are found by their Keepers, blame their Keepers alſo, for they are the<note n="*" place="margin">Of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples rights.</note> looſers, ſo far as they are Raviſhers of Rights.</p>
            <p n="17">17. We are abſolute Slaves, &amp;c. the anſwer afore anſwers this, but I will compleat it: You ſay, but ſhew not how, or in what, or why, for as yet in <hi>Eſſe</hi> you are not, though in <hi>Poſſe</hi> and <hi>Potentia</hi> you ſeemingly are, and will be ſo, for ought I ſee; and when were you otherwiſe? were you not ſo in <hi>Poſſe</hi> and <hi>Potentia</hi> to all your Kings and Governours, ſo alſo to your moſt choice and picked Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments? What could you do, if they would venture their own undoings to undo you, but undo one another? Nay, you alone had in <hi>Eſſe</hi> been undone, had not the Army by their <hi>Potentia</hi> done for you, and relieved you: It's your ſelves then beſlave your ſelves, and ſo forfeit ye your Liberties, by your licentiateneſs, as by your factions, diviſions, and ſeveral ſelf-ends, which hoſtile you one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, yea againſt your own Mother your Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try that bare and brought you up, &amp;c. Surely the ſo divided, are ſoon ſub-divided, and ſo ſubdued, could you forſake your ſelves, it were the only way to find your ſelves; for would you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrize all your particular ends in the<note n="†" place="margin">Or Publique.</note> generals Centre, you would there meet, whereas now you are bemet with, and it would render you powerfully defenſive and offenſive, ſo it's factions that fractions you, <hi>and ſelf ends that divide and undo you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. For let's ſuppoſe no common Governour at all to defend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47355:7"/>of us, or right the wronged, what would become of us all to right our ſelves, but a continuation and addition of wrongs? for what is't that Power and Pravity would not do, and undo? what is't, that luſt, pleaſures, need, and neceſſities would not perpetrate? no Caſtles, Towers, nor houſes would hold us, in points of offence, or defence, for clandeſtines, and treacheries, and Power of one kind or other, would over-power, both circularly, and indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually.</p>
            <p n="19">19. To remedy which, we are fore't by our follies to diſarm our ſelves of offenſive and defenſive Power, for wronging others, of righting our own wrongs, and to venture our ſelves on one or more common Governours (yet truſty and hopeful) Defenders and Protectors, whom we arm with the Sword and Law over us, yet for us, to ſee to, and ſecure us all, both in our rights, and from ruine.</p>
            <p>Now thus diſarmed, and ſuch Governours armed, we are as good as naked in point of power, for defence againſt the ſaid Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, if they would contrary to their Truſt offend us, for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Power enables (but inrights them not) to offend us; but this know, that it's our own doings, as afore, that undo us, and renders us ſlaves in <hi>Poſſe</hi> and <hi>Potentia</hi> to theſe Powers, and it's the wickedneſs of theſe Powers that renders us ſlaves in <hi>Eſſe,</hi> if beyond our doings.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>Ob.</hi> But ſure, this entertaining Kinghood again, is againſt vowes, oaths, promiſes, and proteſts, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Still thou wilt have it Kinghood, be it ſo then, for we will not diſpleaſe thee, ſo not diſpute it. I anſwer, I know not of any ſuch Covenants, or proteſts againſt; &amp;c. but grant all, ſee in part our anſwer in the <hi>Army-Armed,</hi> pag. 15. Sect. 22. to which we add to make all unanſwerable, that in our own ſelf-concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we are bound to ſuffering Covenants, &amp;c. but not to ſinfuls, as are deſtructives, but to anothers unjuſt or injurious ſuffering we may not make, or if made, not keep, except we can make ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Its a ſin to make unlawful, injurious, or ſuffering Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants againſt any one, and its a greater ſin to keep them: Sins ſingle are ſufficient, they cannot be leſſened by addition, or inlargeing; ſo ſuch Covenants are beſt kept by breaking, for their keeping breaks their Keeper, and their careleſs making, mars him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> was juſtly puniſhed; for unjuſtly puniſhing the Gibeonites;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47355:7"/>contrary to Covenant, for they brake not with him, nor was the ſaid Covenant dangerous or deſtructive to him nor his, for they were his ſlaves and ſervile ſervants, and ſo very ſerviceable to him and his people, but had they any way invaded or indangered his rights, he had ſerv'd them rightly to ruine them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No.</hi> 30. The wife could not, nor can in reaſon make any vow at all, no not a pious or holy one, as might the Widdow, a ſelf-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, 'cauſe it invaded her husbands rights, though ſhe wrong'd him not, and though made, it was breakable by her husband,<note place="margin">Sufferingly, yet it was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation and ſo unjuſt.</note> and ſo by her, and God did forgive her, only he taught her to be more wiſe and obedient next time, as not to preſume to uſurp authority over her man, for it was not woman-like; ſo all our Powers, as relating to the publique, are not ſelf-Powers, for they are but wifes to their husbands, the Publiques good and ſafety, ſo may they not make, or if made, not keep, ſuffering, injurious, indangering, or deſtructive Covenants made amongſt our ſelves, againſt their Husband and Head; but if made with a juſtly offended enemy, who being wrong'd, is forc't by force to right himſelf, and hath gain'd power to ruiue his wrongers: I conceive ſuffering, yea indangering Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants are there to be kept, becauſe they are ſhort of preſent ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine,<note place="margin">As we over the Scots.</note> which attends, if the juſt Conquerour be not attended in his demands; ſo a ſuffering Covenant that ſaves, is to be ſaved harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: But this asks more diſpute then this place will allow of, ſo I am not dogmatical, but doubting, and yet, it may be, I am more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid then hurt.</p>
            <p>And whereas laſt of all, thou ſporteſt thy ſelf with thy gay and taunting language of the Angels guarding, this reſerved Eden, this Paradiſe, this place of bliſs and pleaſure, as thou art pleas'd to call it: I anſwer thee, that thou canſt not make good what thou ſayeſt, why then ſayeſt thou it? how makeſt thou it appear to be ſuch a Paradiſe, or place of pleaſure, whereas, when all things are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it will appear otherwiſe? how canſt thou ſay its accepted or aſſum'd, (if ſo thou wiſe have it aſſum'd) as ſuch a place, ſeeing there may be other reaſons for its acceptance, or aſſuming?</p>
            <p>How is't then thou ſtill wilt certain it from uncertainties, as to conclude it of ſelf-end, of Soveraignty, &amp;c.? ſeeing it may as well be from contrary ends,<note place="margin">Things that forbid one to venture on.</note> as from the countermands of neceſſitated publique conducings viz. the peace, welfare, and ſafety of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, which ſeem hazardable by delayes and diviſions in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47355:8"/>for ſhame then humanize and rationalize it, for the Lawes of Love and Logick are ſtill againſt thee, as in doubtfuls to be dogmatical, reſerve then, or remiſs it in judging, till apparent grounds be, and then appear with judgment, or appear not, for if well weighed, vvhat invitations are there for Kinghood, as thou call'ſt it? Surely, ſurprizals do continually attend the moſt attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that they have not the liberty, freedome, or ſerenity of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as have the lower in condition and conditions, but are ever and anon clouded with black and ſwarthy fears of clandeſtines: in their Sun-ſhines, they are Sun-burnt, and in the ſhade, they are<note n="*" place="margin">Too much.</note> over-ſhadowed, with the darkneſs of cares and fears which eclipſe them, and ſo render their mid-dayes, mid-nights: they cannot ſort with their conſorts ſo ſweetly as canſt thou, and their ſleep is but wakeful ſlumberings, for if found, its not ſecure, 'cauſe ſecure, for repoſe, arreſt them with unquietneſs: Sure, thou haſt no ſenſe, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy ſenſes, ſo canſt not ſee inviſibles, for the<note n="*" place="margin">As meer nothings.</note> inviſibles of ſhades and ſur-faces, but couldſt thou penetrate their intrinſiques, they would penetrate thee, and render thee a <hi>Penicent;</hi> for beſides what's afore. Is't nothing to be continually dogged and hunted by a brace of deep and fowl-mouth'd Bloud-hounds, viz. envy and revenge, the one alwayes ſnarling at greatneſs and goodneſs, as a bitter enemy to both, the other raving againſt great and ſmall that croſs them in their wayes, ends, ſuits, or Petitions, which it may be cannot be granted them; Is't nothing to keep in peace an unpeace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, factious, divided, and diſcontented people, and to civilize uncivil war amongſt them, and ſo render their country<note n="†" place="margin">In that point</note> refin'd? Is't nothing to bandy it in arms; and mate the unmatchable? and wiſely correſpond it with all Forraign Princes, Powers, and States, and to prevent or ſupplant their wiles, by<note n="*" place="margin">Wiſdom and policy.</note> wiles? is't nothing to be invironed and over-laid with a world of difficulties paſt reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what to do, or not do, even to deſtraction? is not the peace, freedome, and quictneſs of mind, and a ſecure injoyment of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, far before theſe admired and opinionated glories, which ſure were it not for the publique good, it were a glory to be without them? I dare not ſay all I could ſay, and I am afraid I have already ſaid too much; for I will aſſure thee I cannot find, why any one (all things conſidered) ſhould covet for their ſelf-ends, to wreath, or begirt their Temples with a Crown of Thornes, 'cauſe of gold, or guilded, ſeeing it draws bloud as well from the heart, as the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47355:8"/>head, and from the brain as from both? but the publique good, welfare, peace, and ſafety, muſt be undertaken by ſome, elſe both it and all Privates will ſuffer, and we ought by the Lawes of Love and charity judg it to be the chief ground of its undertaking, till we foe plainly to the contrary, which when thou doſt, contrary me, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But its time I draw to an end, and yet it behoves me before I end humbly to hint and <hi>memorandum,</hi> all Governours of ſome uſeful concernments, relating to themſelves and the people, alſo to do as much by the people in relation to their Governours, in points of judging and cenſuring, &amp;c. <hi>and ſo retaliate each ſide rightly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure, its a hard task on both ſides, as firſt for the wronged peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as they conceive of themſelves, to ſuffer with a ſlaviſh fear and ſilence, or to find no redreſs after a right information, according to the end of Governours and Government, but contrary to both, to be confin'd or compreſt, againſt both which I except, except the common good injoyn, which if it do, I joyn with it, for its own ſake (as neceſſitated) will juſtifie any neceſſicated indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual injuſtice for juſt.</p>
            <p>It's as hard alſo for <hi>Governours,</hi> though never ſo wiſe and juſt, yet to be juſt to all, or if they be, yet to ſatisfie the unjuſt, or juſt, in their wicked or weak exceptions and judgments, nor can the Governour alwayes do Juſtice if he would, for that by-ends and pretences, or falſe witneſs, and fallacious arguments deceive, ſo deviate the beſt of men, and ableſt of judgment, <hi>for the ableſt are not abſolute,</hi> nor can contrary ſuits and Petitions be comply'd to, nor ought, but only the appearing juſt, &amp;c. but then the croſt fall<note n="†" place="margin">Exclaiming.</note> a curſing.</p>
            <p>The wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaw this, yet was ſeemingly over-ſeen, ſo he was forc't to pretend<note n="*" place="margin">As in the Harlots caſes.</note> treachery, to find out truth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Nay, God himſelf, (with reverence be it ſpoken) is not wiſe enough (though wiſdom it ſelf) to deal with ſome wilfuls and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiteds, except he will reverſe or alter nature, or their natures, for is he not ply'd daily and hourely with infinites of contrary and claſhing Petitions; ſome Petition for fair weather for their wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, walks and journeys, or other pleaſures, others for a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhowre to water their gardens, a third ſort for a found one for their grain and graſs; What ſhall the wiſe and juſt God doe with theſe weaklings, who for ſelf-ends oppoſe nature, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47355:9"/>God of nature, ſo one another, and the <hi>General,</hi> and petition and importune God to alter or reverſe nature, only to grace them.</p>
            <p>Winds contrary almoſt all, for they can content but from one Coaſt at once, but God is petitioned from all Coaſts, parts, and points of the world, by infinite contrary and diſſenting Petitioners; how ſhall he do, except he undo all, as afore, and ſo he ſhall have enough to do, for if he hearken to one, the reſt will not hearken to him, 'cauſe it contraries them; and if he hearken to all he cannot hear any at all, for all of them oppoſe one another, and him alſo; ſo to pleaſe them all, he muſt diſpleaſe them all, and bring winds from each part or point of the compaſs or circumference to meet in the Center-point, and there to abide and oppoſe each other, till theſe weaklings learn more wit, and agree, that the winds ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their places again, and they will hence-forward take their turns and places. Thus we may ſee that there is a world of fooliſh <hi>Zebedean</hi> and giddy-brain'd <hi>Phaeton</hi> Petitioners and Suiters, that know not what they would or ſhould have, and only here and there a<note n="*" place="margin">A wiſe man.</note> 
               <hi>Phoebus,</hi> that knows what to ask and forego, and why, and why not, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Some ſet the <hi>Beacon</hi> on <hi>fire,</hi> others quench it, <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water</hi> fall out and oppoſe,<note place="margin">Two books that oppoſed about books.</note> and in revenge (to right themſelves, or to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by might) Petition againſt each other, both would be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd to, and yet it may be reither can, but a third muſt; how ſhall the wiſeſt and beſt of <hi>Governours</hi> do to keep the <hi>Beacon</hi> burning, and yet quench it?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Laity</hi> would no <hi>Tythes,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> would, eager Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and arguments are on each ſides, and it may be fallacious alſo; the fallacious are true to the abuſed <hi>Governour,</hi> and the true falſe; til he be fully inform'd, he muſt then of neceſſity (right or wrong) comply to the moſt appearing right; for the wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in doubtfuls, was almoſt to ſeek what to do, ſo was fore'd to diſſemble<note n="†" place="margin">As to kill the living child.</note> treachery, to find out the Traytor.</p>
            <p>Henceforward then compreſs, ſilence, or remiſs it, in judging ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely of Governours actions, ſo of their granting or denying of Suits and Petitions, except plain and apparent, and then I will not appear for them, nor againſt thee, nor yet I will, if they make not inquiſition for truth, and a diſquiſition of falſhood, but perfunctorily paſs over both, as willing to be deceived, that ſo they may deceive; blame alſo thy Adverſary that would deceive the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47355:9"/>Governours, and ſo thee, ſo blame thy ſelf, if thou wouldſt the ſame, for thy ſelf-ends, and know, that the <hi>croſs</hi> may juſtly expect to be croſt, yet are too oft bleſt, and comply'd to, and the comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing croſt.</p>
            <p>And now oh you Governours of all ſorts, as I have done you all the right I can, ſo it next concerns me to do the people right alſo, what ſhould I ſay to you more then I have ſaid, and you already know? you are betruſted to the height of betruſt, for they have King'd you, or rather Goded you in point of power, and ſo God himſelf faith, I have ſaid ye are Gods, &amp;c. but yet remember you are but men, and muſt die like them; have they not put into your hands all that is neer and dear to them? as their Lawes, Lives, and Livelyhood, Liberties, and Religion, and have accommodated you with Honors and Revenues accordingly; and laſtly, oathed you in their behalfes; Need I ſay how theſe ingage? ſure I need not, for make it but your own caſes, and the caſe is altered, do then as you would be done to, more is not required, nor leſs can, yet leſs will and ſhall; for we know you cannot do all you ſhould or would for what you cannot: Set before you a Deaths Head, as Kings have done, or let ſome of the ſervants mind you in your pleaſures and paſtimes, ſo at your repaſts, feſtivals, and bunquetings, as did a King with this Memento, <hi>Remember, ob King, that then art but a man,</hi> &amp;c. you cannot preſume of a moment (though Gods) ſo momentary are you; therefore this inſtant endeavour to make good the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples betruſt and hopes all you can, that when you are gone, your names may live honorably famous to eternity, you may be ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpriz'd by ſickneſs or death, or a thouſand caſualties, oh caſt to prevent caſting, by prudently providing for the people, and your own poſterities and kindred (which in infinity of time may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite) to leave them as free as you can; though not free, which in this world will never be, leave them not ſlaves to any Powers when you are gone, more then will prevent their ſlaveries, for there is no bondage like a licentiate liberty, nor any freedom like a wiſe reſtraint, that ſo by the obſervance of the aforeſaids, men (what they may) may be diſtinguiſhed from beaſts. But it's time I end, for I fear I have been over-bold, and ſo tireſome in matter, manner, and extent, but we hope our fair intentions will be look't on, and not over-look't.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47355:10"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>A Word or two about the <hi>Ordinance,</hi> what ſhall be <hi>Treaſon.</hi> Truly we conceiv'd, that by our aforeſaid lines, all clamors would have been huſht and laid, but our <hi>Proſepopaeia</hi> finds that the <hi>Ordinance</hi> hath by the wickedneſſe of ſome, and weakneſſe of other-ſome, heightened them, in that they dare it yet higher, and march it like furious <hi>Ichn,</hi> in their movings and onſets: For, now (ſay they) it appears plainly to be <hi>uſurpation,</hi> in that feare attends guilt, and force and fraud attend fear, and ſo muſt fortifie for it: So theſe have brought forth this aforeſaid<note n="*" place="margin">The Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> 
               <hi>Monſter</hi> (againſt truth) which Powers make by the Ordinance: thus to ſupport<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful uſurpation, as call'd.</note> treachery, all true men muſt Be made traytors, that ſpeak, write, preach or act ſo and ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it's not uſurpation, I have already clear'd it; and were it uſurpation (with our cautions) I yet have or, will cleare it from the injuſtice of their clamors. And were it uſurpation abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, yet as qualified it's clearable from their clamors, as we ſhall ſhew. However (if uſurpation) yet we cleare it (by our follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arguments) from being ſo, from their arguments of fortifying by an Ordinance, &amp;c. Place then, if thou pleaſe, juſtice and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency on the <hi>Throne,</hi> yet there <hi>antagonists, envy, malice,</hi> and <hi>revenge</hi> will endeavour their dethroning. Needs it not then that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for themſelves? Nay would God himſelf perſonally inthrone it, there is that would diſcepter and unthrone him: truly <hi>Samuel</hi> they have depoſed me, for they have outed me as well as thee; they are a ſimple, a wilfull and rebellious people <hi>Samuel,</hi> for they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know not care what they ſay or do.</p>
            <p>Again, have not all the beſt, and moſt innocent Princes, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Potentates been inforc'd to ſecure their ſafety? Nay, were it not trechery, not ſelfly to ſecure it? And were it not trechery to the publike (as its peace and ſafety are concern'd) not to ſecure the ſo<note n="*" place="margin">His High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> 
               <hi>concern'd,</hi> can either the Protector or protected be ſecure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good ſecurity? is not ſupineneſſe in either treaſon to both? How can any protector protect except protected?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47355:10"/>
            <p> Had it not then been made treaſon by an Ordinance, yet Religion, Reaſon, Nature and neceſſity ordain it ſo, ſo then thou hadſt been no leſſe a traytor then now thou art, though thou hadſt<note n="*" place="margin">By a Wr<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Law.</note> not been one. Sure there is a tranſgreſſion where is no<note n="†" place="margin">Writ.</note> law, 'cauſe there is a <note n="*" place="margin">In nature.</note> law to hamper the lawleſſe. Might each one kill, murther, rob and rape it, till trembling mount <hi>Sinai</hi> with aſtoniſhing, thunder and lightning proclaim'd an Ordinance againſt them? This is enough to prove that thou uſurpeſt on thy argument, to infer uſurpation from what's no argument.</p>
            <p>I have hinted on my Title, to allow the people their uttermoſt liberties in chuſing their Governors, &amp;c. which I will do for this once, though this once be once too much. Suppoſe then, all the capable of chuſing, according to former Lawes and Cuſtomes are met on <hi>Salisbury</hi> plaine, to chuſe their governour or governours and government, certainly you ſhall there ſee repreſented the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os</hi> again, or <hi>Babels</hi> confuſion; for few or none of them knowes what they ſhould have, nor well what they would. And did any know what they ſhould or would, yet infinite of ignorants and wilfull ones ſo oppoſe them, that they are <hi>poſed</hi> or <hi>depoſed:</hi> Oh what a confuſed noiſe of contradictions and clamors that is among them, like the jangling of bells rung backward I ſo that if <hi>Cuſhi</hi> ſhould bring us the tidings, what could he ſay but that he ſaw 2 great multitude, but could not tell what to make thereof, as they could not of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Here's a Party for his <hi>Highneſs</hi> that now is, there's another for the King of Scots that now is not, here's ſeveral others for divers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals, their friends, to King or Protector them: Some again are not for any Individual Governour at all, but are all for a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Councel of State, &amp;c. Thoſe for Individuals fall out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, each for his man, and with Parliaments, &amp;c. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their men; thoſe for Parliaments, &amp;c. fall out with thoſe who are for any individual Governour whatſoever, ſo with themſelves about their own individuals of Parliament; ſuppoſe the vote for a Parliament carry it, then the Parliament ſo choſen, may in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood faction it for their chooſers, ſo themſelves and theirs. Thus by-ends turn by the right end, as the Publiques peace, ſafety, and welfare, and the croſt fall a curſing and rage it, high affrontings and darings are, and revenge revels it, and arrives to hand-conteſts, out-flies the flaming Semiters on all ſides, ſo that each brother like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47355:11"/>
               <hi>Ioabs</hi> and <hi>Abners gallants,</hi> is ready to <hi>thrill</hi> his brother. Suppoſe his Highneſs, whileſt Lord General, ſeeing this, ſhould with his Souldiery ſuddainly ſurround and ſurprize them all, and make them his Priſoners, and ſo Freemen, by delivering them from themſelves, and ſo from one another, and by diſarming, arm them, and then ſend them home in ſafety, willing them not to fall out by the way, for chat they are Brethren; and ſhould thereupon (as thus neceſſitated for his own and Souldiers ſafety, ſo the Publiques) mount the Throne, put on the Crown, and aſſume the Scepter, &amp;c. and ſo King it, intitle, &amp;c. as thus intitled thereto; I demand, is this uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, I, or no? the weakling it may be will have it ſo, 'cauſe it's without the univerſal choice of the people; but the wiſe man ſaith, that its not uſurpation, 'cauſe choſen by his own deſerts, ſo by the peoples deſires, &amp;c. (as by their neceſſities of peace and ſafety) for what have we to do, ſaith the wiſe man, with <hi>articulate</hi> choice, if juſt neceſſities article againſt it? Now if the ſo choſen ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducingly protect and govern us, which I hope he will, I pray you then allow him what he hath, at leaſt, ſeeing they who had much more, did much leſs.</p>
            <p>To conclude, what did <hi>Saul,</hi> or <hi>Sauls</hi> Son <hi>David</hi> for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, to this our Son of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> for their <hi>Kinghoods?</hi> one of them was fetch't from ſeeking <hi>Aſſes,</hi> the other from folding of <hi>Sheep,</hi> yet (for killing a Giant at diſtance, whom it may be he durſt not come neer) was as good as King'd; but our <hi>David</hi> hath apparently (and not of ſelf-report only) kill'd many Lions Bears and Giants, ſo is juſtly (as well as <hi>David</hi>) choſen for his deſerts, beſides twice of the People, as I have proved, yet of the deſertleſſe, ſhould be deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>though thus aſſerted, were it not for, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>DIXI.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47355:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
